## MD. FAHAD BIN SIDDIQUE

LL.M (International Law), East West University
LL.M (SAF Madanjeet Singh Scholarship), UMSAILS
MBA (HRM), School of Business & Economics, North South University

Apartment B-6, Rupayan Khan Tower 51 West Hazipara, Malibagh Chowdhurypara Dhaka 1219, Bangladesh +88 01676 521226 fahadbinsiddique@gmail.com



## **PROFILE**

Md. Fahad Bin Siddique is an apprentice of the District Court of Dhaka, Bangladesh. He is currently an Associate of Siddique Law Assign, a Law Chambers based in Dhaka, Bangladesh, and working as a Research Associate of Dr. Md Mahatab Uddin, Professor (Adjunct), University of Guelph, Canada. His areas of interest include Public International Law, Intellectual Property Law, International Commercial Arbitration, Humanitarian & Refugee Law, among others.

Upon receiving a SAF Madanjeet Singh Scholarship sponsored by the South Asia Foundation (an apex body of the SAARC), Mr. Fahad pursued LL.M at the UNESCO Madanjeet Singh South Asian Institute of Advanced Legal and Human Rights Studies (UMSAILS) jointly organised with University of Asia Pacific, Dhaka, Bangladesh. Mr. Fahad also completed a Master of Business Administration (MBA) in Human Resource Management from North South University, Dhaka, Bangladesh. Before that, he has done LL.M in International Law at the East West University, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

He previously worked as an Associate (Corporate & Commercial Practice) in Rahman & Rabbi Legal, a corporate and commercial law chamber based in Dhaka, Bangladesh. He also worked with Bangladesh Legal Aid and Services Trust (BLAST), a Human Rights Organization based in Bangladesh. He has publications in journals on different law and social topics. He is an occasional contributor to national dailies.

### PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Served in a team which advised a UK based Multinational Tobacco Company regarding employment contract and termination process of employees under the concerning laws of Bangladesh

Served in a team which advised a Multinational Company regarding the advertisement of tobacco products and possible consequences of this type of advertising under tobacco-related laws of Bangladesh

Served in a team which advised a Multinational Company on the legal consequence of the inclusion of a non-compete clause in the employment contract and the procedure of complying with the clause under the existing laws of Bangladesh

Served in a team which advised a scheduled bank of Bangladesh regarding the acceptance of the electronic form of cheques (e-cheques) and truncated cheques under the auspices of local laws and customary international law & practice relating to banking as well as negotiation instruments

Served in a team which represented a UK based Multinational Tobacco Company in a number of litigation regarding the infringement of trademark of one of its major brands and passing off its products

Served in a team which has been conducted several formal mediation processes regarding various family and labour matters under the family law and labour law of Bangladesh

### CHAMBERS HISTORY

*Associate* at **Siddique Law Assign**, Suite 214 (1st Floor), Rupayan Kamaruddin Tower, 8/A, DIT Road, Dhaka 1219, Bangladesh (May 2020 – Present)

Associate (Corporate & Commercial Practice) at Rahman & Rabbi Legal, Suite 1206, SEL Rose-N-Dale, 116 Kazi Nazrul Islam Avenue, Eskaton, Dhaka 1000, Bangladesh, <a href="www.randrl.com">www.randrl.com</a> (March 2019 – April 2020)

*Trainee* at **Makbul Ahmed and Associates**, Al-Helal Bhaban, 186 Motijheel Circular Road, Arambag, Dhaka 1000, Bangladesh. (February 2016 – July 2016)

## **APPOINTMENTS**

**Research Associate** of Dr. Md Mahatab Uddin, Professor (Adjunct) at **University of Guelph**, Canada & Visiting Researcher at **International Centre for Climate Change and Development (ICCCAD)**, one of the leading research and capacity building organisations in Bangladesh (November 2021 - Present)

*Legal Intern* at Bangladesh Legal Aid and Services Trust (BLAST), one of the leading Human Rights organisations in Bangladesh (September 2018 – December 2018)

## PUBLICATION (BOOK CHAPTER)

Fahad Bin Siddique (Co-author), 'Farmers' Participatory Practices of Adopting Digital Communication Technologies for Climate-Smart Agriculture: Bangladesh Perspectives' in Digital Communication for Agricultural and Rural Development: Participatory Practices in a Post-Covid Age (Taylor & Francis 2023) (Accepted)

Fahad Bin Siddique (Co-author), 'An Overview of the Trademark Regime of Bangladesh: TRIPS Compatibility Perspectives' in *Handbook of Intellectual Property Laws of Bangladesh* (Accepted and will be published from abroad)

## PUBLICATION (JOURNAL ARTICLE)

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'The Doctrine of Fair Use in the Aspect of Covid-19 Pandemic: Perspective of Copyright Laws in Bangladesh', *University of Asia Pacific Law Review*, Vol. 1, Issue 1 [2021] p 47-57.

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Champerty vs. Third Party Funding in Arbitration: A Censorious Debate', *SCLS Law Review*, Vol. 3, Issue 3 [September 2020] p 66-72. ISSN (Online): 2523-9236, ISSN (Print): 2523-9228

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Non-Refoulement and other Durable Solutions in Refugee Law: Rohingyas in Perspective', *SCLS Law Review*, Vol. 2, Issue 1 [January 2019] p 19-28. ISSN (Online): 2523-9236, ISSN (Print): 2523-9228

### **CONFERENCE PAPER**

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Doctrine of Fair Use in the Aspect of Covid-19: Bangladesh Perspective' (Paper presented at UMSAILS-UAP International Conference on the Impact of Covid-19 Pandemic in the Legal Field, 17-19 June 2021, organised by <u>UMSAILS</u> & <u>University of Asia Pacific</u>)

## PUBLICATION (NEWSPAPER ARTICLE)

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'We should be concerned about the prisoners' human rights in Bangladesh', *The Business Standard*, published on 24 November 2021

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Mergers and acquisitions: Analysing an Indian experience from a Bangladeshi standpoint', *Dhaka Tribune*, published on 29 October 2021

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Election, international law & United Nations', The Business Standard, published on 18 October 2021

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Absence of adequate legal framework for e-cheques', *The Daily Star*, published on 24 December 2019

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Non-compete clause: Can employer impose restraint upon former employees?', *The Daily Star*, published on 20 August 2019

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Punishment in Educational Institutions', *The Daily Star*, published on 18 December 2018

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'User's Privacy in Using Apps', *The Daily Star*, published on 20 November 2018

Fahad Bin Siddique (Co-author), 'New media, new rules: How should Bangladesh go about regulating the OTT sector?', *Dhaka Tribune*, published on 21 September 2020

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'In a grey area of copyright legislation: How do copyright laws apply to the concept of ghostwriting?', *Dhaka Tribune*, published on 05 September 2020

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'A rising attribute: What third-party funding in international commercial arbitration could mean for Bangladesh', *Dhaka Tribune*, published on 16 July 2020

Fahad Bin Siddique (Co-author), 'Appropriate jurisdiction in trademark infringement', *The Daily Observer*, published on 22 February 2020

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Rape and the Promise of Marriage', *The Daily Observer*, published on 22 December 2018

Fahad Bin Siddique, '**Advertisement by Legal Professionals**', *The Daily Observer*, published on 20 September 2018

Fahad Bin Siddique, 'Comparative Advertisement in Bangladesh', *The Daily Observer*, published on 18 October 2018

## UNPUBLISHED RESEARCH

Completed the thesis entitled 'Introducing Waiver of Moral Rights in Bangladesh Copyright Law: A Comparative Study with the UK' in fulfilment of the requirement for the award of the degree of LL.M at the UNESCO Madanjeet Singh South Asian Institute of Advanced Legal and Human Rights Studies (UMSAILS)

Completed the thesis entitled 'Cyber Security: Comprehensive Study and Remedies in Bangladesh Perspective' in fulfilment of the requirement for the award of the degree of LL.B (Honours) at the Stamford University Bangladesh

## MOOT COMPETITION, CONFERENCE & WORKSHOP

Participated at the Moot Court Competition titled '4th Intra-Department Moot Court Competition' held at University of Asia Pacific and organised by Department of Law & Human Rights and UAP Moot Court Club

Participated at the Workshop titled 'Legal Research and Advocacy Skills' held at East West University and organised by Network for International Law Students Bangladesh (NILS)

Participated as an observer at the Conference titled 'International Conference on International Law' held at East West University and organised by Department of Law, East West University in partnership with Network for International Law Students Bangladesh (NILS)

Participated as an observer at the Conference titled 'International Conference on Sustainability in Natural and Built Environment' held at North South University and this conference was a collaborative initiative among several organisations including North South University, Solar-e-

Technology (Sydney), EnviroWater (Sydney), Western Sydney University, University of Dhaka and Daffodil International University

## **ACADEMIC QUALIFICATION**

# UNESCO Madanjeet Singh South Asian Institute of Advanced Legal and Human Rights Studies (UMSAILS) In collaboration with University of Asia Pacific, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Master of Laws (LL.M)

Graduation: 2021 CGPA: 3.43

Honours: Recipient of the SAF Madanjeet Singh Scholarship, South Asian Foundation (an

apex body of the SAARC)

## North South University, Dhaka, Bangladesh

School of Business & Economics (SBE)
MBA in **Human Resource Management** 

Graduation: 2021 CGPA: 3.08

Honours: Secured **Best Paper Award** (Second) at UMSAILS-UAP International Conference

on the Impact of Covid-19 Pandemic in the Legal Field

## East West University, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Department of Law

Master of Laws (LL.M) in International Law

Graduation: 2018 CGPA: 3.84

<u>Honours</u>: Secured **first position** in the batch

## Stamford University Bangladesh, Dhaka

Faculty of Law

Bachelor of Laws (LL.B) (Honours)

Graduation: 2016 CGPA: 3.01

## Dhaka Public College, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Board of Intermediate and Secondary Education, Dhaka

Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC)

Division: Science Graduation: 2011

GPA: 3.40

## Motijheel Model High School, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Board of Intermediate and Secondary Education, Dhaka

Secondary School Certificate (SSC)

Division: Science Graduation: 2009

GPA: 4.44

### AWARD & ACADEMIC SCHOLARSHIP

Recipient of the 'SAF Madanjeet Singh Scholarship' from UNESCO Madanjeet Singh South Asian Institute of Advanced Legal and Human Rights Studies (UMSAILS) in the academic year of 2020-2021. The scholarship was sponsored by the South Asia Foundation (SAF), founded by UNESCO Goodwill Ambassador Madanjeet Singh. SAF has been recognised as an Apex Body of the South Asian Association of Regional Cooperation (SAARC).

Recipient of the 'Best Paper Award (Second)' for the paper titled 'Doctrine of fair use in the aspect of Covid-19: Bangladesh Perspective' presented at the UMSAILS-UAP International Conference on the Impact of Covid-19 Pandemic in the Legal Field, organised by UNESCO Madanjeet Singh South Asian Institute of Advanced Legal and Human Rights Studies (UMSAILS) and Department of Law and Human Rights, University of Asia Pacific.

### **GENERAL INFORMATION**

**Father** : Md. Siddigur Rahman

Advocate, District Court, Dhaka, Bangladesh

**Mother** : Mrs. Sultana

Housewife

**Status** : Single

**Date of birth** : 05 June, 1993 **National ID** : 8250715979

**Religion** : Islam

### REFERENCE

### Dr. Md Mahatab Uddin

Adjunct Professor,

University of Guelph, Canada

Post-doctoral Fellow,

University of Southern Denmark, Denmark

Visiting Researcher,

International Centre for Climate Change and Development (ICCCAD)

E-mail: mmu.env@gmail.com

## Md. Monzur Rabbi

Fulbright Scholar

University of Miami School of Law

Barrister-at-Law (Lincoln's Inn)

Advocate, Supreme Court of Bangladesh

Phone: +880 258317587 E-mail: rabbi@randrl.com